César Garro-Marín

Ph.D Candidate • Economics • Boston University

☐ (857) 425-9404 • ☑ cesarlgm@bu.edu • ❸ cesargarromarin.com • in cesarlgm

About me

Ph.D candidate in Economics with a strong background in data analysis and causal inference. Interested in economist and data scientist positions. Over 8 years of experience in Stata and R. A team player and a manager, having worked on multiple cross-functional projects. Lead project development & management, as well as data collection, coding, statistical & econometric analysis.

Work Experience

Boston University.

Research a thesis titled "Essays in Gender, Earnings and Geography", which studies the importance of local labor markets and firms for explaining gender and earnings inequality.

Lead Researcher — Project manager: Boston, MA, USA / Jakarta, IDN, 2020-Present

Partnered with Indonesian policymakers & a fellow BU student to assess the impact of vocational school training programs, identified effectiveness challenges, & delivered practical recommendations to policymakers for program improvement. Successfully secured \$75,000 from external grants.

- Defined effectiveness metrics & designed an experimental evaluation for the program, which was then deployed in coordination with the Indonesian Ministry of Education
- Designed & deployed an original survey to collect data from 2,000 teachers & managed a team of research assistants & surveyors
- Responsible for presenting findings & policy recommendations to senior policymakers (non-technical roles).

Graduate Student Researcher — Research Assistant: Boston, MA, 2019–Present

Researched the role of local labor markets in explaining gender inequality, the role of firms in explaining labor market outcomes, & how people invest in skills. Used rich micro data to test hypotheses, infer causal mechanisms, design data visualizations, & provide valuable insights on how the local environment & individual decisions affect labor market outcomes.

- Cleaned and analyzed large & intricate datasets to extract valuable insights on gender inequality, local labor markets, earnings disparities within the US academic sector, & people's skill investment. Worked with large census & survey data from multiple countries and created compelling data visualizations with R, Matlab, and Stata.
- Created & oversaw multiple research projects on labor & development economics using reduced-form & structural research designs
- Responsible for presenting findings in internal departmental seminars as well as international conferences

Teaching Fellow: Boston, MA, Sep 2019- Sep 2020

Delivered lectures to students at both the undergraduate and graduate level. Took special attention to convey intuitions and simplify complex concepts.

University of Costa Rica

Instructor: San José, Costa Rica, Jun 2014–Jun 2015

Taught Principles to Economics to non-economics students

- Developed lesson plans, homework, and grading schema, and wrote detailed feedback on homework and exams
- Held weekly office hours for individualized tutoring

Bac-Credomatic Bank.....

One of the leading banks in Central America and Costa Rica. Largest private bank and leading credit card issuer in Costa Rica. Data analyst: San José, Costa Rica, Jan 2013–June 2014

Provided critical product insights to senior bank executives by analyzing credit card portfolio data.

- Designed & executed data analysis for the bank's senior management & other internal clients, informing decisions about credit policy, credit offering targeting, & debt collection targeting
- Monitored industry trends & measured product performance to proactively identify opportunities for improvement & growth
 Lead automation of regular reports, & maintained robust documentation of procedures & software

Education

Ph.D. Economics 2017- 2023 (expected) Boston University, Boston, MA

2015-2017

2009-2013

M.A. Economics & Finance

Center for Monetary and Financial Studies, Madrid, Spain

B.A. Economics (with honors)

Universidad de Costa Rica, San José, Costa Rica

Skills

Project: experimental design, long-term project management, team management. Data analysis: causal inference, data visualization, large data manipulation, statistical analysis & testing. Communication: Science writing, Annotation, Public speaking. Technologies: R, Matlab, Stata, Git, SQL, LATEX. Languages: English (Bilingual proficiency), Spanish (Native), French (basic)

References

References available upon request